Guide to the Rust Engineering Company Records, 1905-1989 AIS.2006.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Photographs, 1914-1967; IX.
  This series contains over 400 prints and negatives depicting Rust Engineering's construction sites, offices, personnel, and events such as banquets and recognition ceremonies. The majority of the photographs had been housed in three albums, two containing images of job sites and machinery from the 1920s through the 1950s, and one documenting the construction of coke processing facilities and blast furnaces for Central Iron and Coal Company in Holt, Alabama, between 1917 and 1918. The Holt album covers many stages of the large project and also includes rare images of the working conditions and the surrounding town. "Before and after" images, found in all albums, follow progress at construction sites and show the types of tools, scaffolding, and underlying foundations used to build a variety of structures.
  Many of the loose photographs appear to have been taken for publication, either in Rust's advertising brochures and leaflets or for the Rust Triangle newsletter. Please note that some photographs are stamped with the name of a photographer or studio. They remain the intellectual property of the creator and cannot be reproduced without permission.
  Digital reproductions of the collection are available online.
  - Job Album 1, 1.
    - Framework for "Rutherfords job" (Job #6059), Grammercy, LA, June 8, 1950 (Box 80, Folder 1)
    - Boilers, Consolidated Gas Co. Hunts Point, NY (Box 80, Folder 2)
    - Coke plant, Koppers Seaboard Coke Company, Brooklyn, NY (Box 80, Folder 3)
    - Construction work on a plant for International Cement, Washington, D.C., c1925 (Box 80, Folder 4)
    - Gunite work and bridge construction for the Pennsylvania RR. Co., Hunts Point, NY (Job #2114) (Box 80, Folder 5)
    - Gunite work, Riverside Drive, NYC (Job #1870), December, 1927-1928, July 8, 1927 (Box 80, Folder 6)
    - Monitor ends for Chevrolet Plant, Atlanta, GA (Job #1978), March 1928 (Box 80, Folder 7)
    - Completed bridge for the New Jersey Highway Commission, 1966 (Box 80, Folder 8)
    - Steam engine and completed floor system of New York Ave. Bridge, Washington, D.C., October 1931 (Box 80, Folder 9)
    - Ordnance Department, Picatinny Arsenal Packing House, M-4344, March 23, 1932 (Box 80, Folder 10)
    - Completed Route 30 Bridge for the D.L and W.R.R., April 25, 1932 (Box 80, Folder 11)
    - Workers applying concrete to a nine foot wind tunnel for the Georgia School of Technology, Atlanta, GA, May 1930 (Box 80, Folder 12)
    - Installation of three Springfield Boilers for Consolidated Gas Co., Hunts Point, NY, c1925 (Box 80, Folder 13)
    - Completed bridge for L.V. RR Co. and Essex County Park Commission, Newark, N.J. (Job #2778-2779), October 10, 1932 (Box 80, Folder 14)
    - Before and after shots of Geary Boiler installation for Pittsburgh and West Virginia Gas Co., Downs, W.V., c1925 (Box 80, Folder 15)
    - Domestic screening plant for Koppers Seaboard Coke Co., Kearney, N.J. (Box 80, Folder 16)
    - Construction of Lake Street Bridge, Ashtabula, Ohio (Job #2088), October 31, 1928 (Box 80, Folder 17)
    - Workers applying gunite to a fur vault for Joseph Horne Warehouse, Pittsburgh, PA, March 17, 1928 (Box 80, Folder 18)
    - Load test for chimney bearing (Job #1692), July 4, 1925 (Box 80, Folder 19)
    - Completed boilers, location unknown (Box 80, Folder 20)
    - Boiler installation, location unknown, c1925 (Box 80, Folder 21)
    - Monitor ends for Chevrolet plant, Atlanta, G.A. (Job #1978) (Box 80, Folder 22)
    - Coal silo for Utica Gas and Electric Co., Utica, NY, c1925 (Box 80, Folder 23)
    - Construction and brickwork in an unknown building, July 19, 1924 (Box 80, Folder 24)
    - Bridge walls for Metropolitan Power Co., Middletown, PA., 1926 (Box 80, Folder 25)
    - Tangentially fired burner for Ford, Walkerville, Ontario (Box 80, Folder 26)
    - Completed boiler installation for Penn. American Refining Co., Oil City, PA, c1925 (Box 80, Folder 27)
    - Boiler installation, location unknown (Box 80, Folder 28)
    - Interior shot of unknown building, Binghamton, NY (Box 80, Folder 29)
    - Super-power station for Ohio River Edison Company, Toronto, Ohio, January 17, 1925 (Box 80, Folder 30)
    - Interior brickwork, location unknown, c1925 (Box 80, Folder 31)
    - Garbage incinerator, Garden City, NY (Box 80, Folder 32)
    - Building and power plant for Ford Motor Company (Job #1347), 1924 (Box 80, Folder 33)
    - Workers building 75th Street Bridge over Village Creek, November 1931 (Box 80, Folder 34)
    - Pennsylvania State Highway Bridge at Groveton, Pa, 1929 (Box 80, Folder 35)
  - Job Album 2, 2.
    - Chimneys, stills, plants, and other work for Pennzoil Co., Oil City, Pa (Job #1728, 1777), 1926 (Box 81, Folder 1)
    - Gunite work on a bridge for New Jersey State Highway Commission, Newark, NJ (Job #1966), January 4-December 16, 1927 (Box 81, Folder 2)
    - Overpass bridge for New Jersey State Highway Commission (Job #2233), March 19, 1929 (Box 81, Folder 3)
    - Exterior shot of building for Aracoma Laundry Company, Logan, WV (Box 81, Folder 4)
    - Garage and car showroom for Dawley Motor Company, c1925 (Box 81, Folder 5)
    - Coke and coal bins for Northern Indiana Gas and Electric Co., Fort Wayne, Indiana (Box 81, Folder 6)
    - Construction of a nine foot wind tunnel for Georgia Tech, Atlanta, GA, May 1931 (Box 81, Folder 7)
    - Workers building Brighton Road and W. North Ave. Bridge, Pittsburgh, PA (Box 81, Folder 8)
    - Overlooking town and construction of Winchester Ave. Overpass, Ashland, KY, September 14, 1932 (Box 81, Folder 9)
    - Workers and cranes, construction of D.L & W. R.R. Main Line, Washington, NJ (Job #2766), June-December, 1931 (Box 81, Folder 10)
    - Completed gunite power house for Phoenix Utility Company, Phoenix, AZ (Job #2405)February 14, 1930 (Box 81, Folder 11)
    - Floor system of New York Ave. Bridge, Washington, D.C., October, 1931 (Box 81, Folder 12)
    - Lake Street Bridge, Ashtebula, Ohio (Job #2088), November 1, 1928 (Box 81, Folder 13)
    - Gunite repair to Q. Street Bridge, Washington, D.C. (Job #2863), August 31, 1932 (Box 81, Folder 14)
    - New Philadelphia, O.3" reinforced gunite lining (Job #2765), October 19, 1931 (Box 81, Folder 15)
    - Gunite application, Payson Park Reservoir, Cambridge, MA (Job #1838), September 8, 1927 (Box 81, Folder 16)
    - Ordnance Department Picatinny Arsenal, Cannon powder blender M-4245, 1929 (Box 81, Folder 17)
    - Construction of Bell Telephone Company Building addition, Pittsburgh, PA, 1929 (Box 81, Folder 18)
    - Gunite application, location unknown, February 21, 1928 (Box 81, Folder 19)
    - Chevropet Plant (Box 81, Folder 20)
    - Niagara Street Bridge for NJ State Highway Commission, Newark, NJ, 1927 (Box 81, Folder 21)
    - Bridge, location unknown, August 8, 1928 (Box 81, Folder 22)
    - P. RR bridge, Arcade, NY, October, 1929 (Box 81, Folder 23)
    - Exterior and office shots of an assembly plant for Ford Motor Company, Chester, PA, 1927 (Box 81, Folder 24)
  - Banquet Photos, 3.
    - Veteran Employee's Dinner, October 25, 1946 (Box 81, Folder 25)
    - Founders Day and Service Award Dinner, University Club, Pittsburgh, October 27, 1950 (Box 82, Folder 1)
    - Service Award Banquet commemorating the company's fiftieth anniversary, Hotel William Penn, Pittsburgh, PA, October 19, 1955 (Box 82, Folder 2)
    - Sixtieth Anniversary and Fifth Service Banquet, Hotel Webster Hall, Pittsburgh, PA and Parliament House, Birmingham, AL, November 11, 1965, December 7, 1965 (Box 82, Folder 3)
    - Banquet booklets, 1950-1955 (Box 82, Folder 4)
    - General banquet information, 1964-1965 (Box 82, Folder 5)
    - Quarter Century Club, 1985-1995 (Box 82, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Photos, 4.
    - Rust Boiler Shop, 1905 (Box 82, Folder 7)
    - Extension to the government printing office, Washington, D.C., September 3, 1929 (Box 82, Folder 8)
    - Building and bricklayers in a building, location unknown, May 8, 1929 (Box 82, Folder 9)
    - Office building for National Gas Co., Clarksburg, WV, May 8, 1929 (Box 82, Folder 10)
    - Shots of employees in the first Pittsburgh office, located in the Farmers Bank Building, 1917 (Box 82, Folder 11)
    - Boston Office building, Boston, MA, 1956 (Box 82, Folder 12)
    - S.M. Rust and Coppee-Rust officers, August 13, 1964 (Box 82, Folder 13)
    - Rust Engineering Award for high school students, March 28, 1950 (Box 83, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified building and train tracks, July 21, 1950 (Box 83, Folder 2)
    - Unknown plant, October 25, 1950 (Box 83, Folder 3)
    - Banquet at University Club, October 30, 1950 (Box 83, Folder 4)
    - Photo of a drawing of a warehouse and office building for Kroger Company, Pittsburgh, PA, March 23, 1951 (Box 83, Folder 5)
    - Brickwork, July 11, 1951 (Box 83, Folder 6)
    - Interior and exterior shots, J&L plant, Hazelwood, October 22, 1951 (Box 83, Folder 7)
    - J&L Aliquippa, October 24, 1951 (Box 83, Folder 8)
    - Hubbard Aluminum Products Co. building, November 9, 1951 (Box 83, Folder 9)
    - Two men at desk in Rust building at Sixth Ave. and Diamond, Pittsburgh, PA, August 15, 1952 (Box 83, Folder 10)
    - Rust building at Sixth Ave. and Diamond, March 25, 1952 (Box 83, Folder 11)
    - Rust building at Sixth Ave. and Diamond, April 2, 1952 (Box 83, Folder 12)
    - Retouched image of Rust building at Sixth Ave. and Diamond, May 27, 1942 (Box 83, Folder 13)
    - Ceremony for winners of the Rust Technology Award, Duquesne Club, Pittsburgh, PA, February 1929, 1956 (Box 83, Folder 14)
    - Rust Technology Award, winning drawings, March 2, 1957 (Box 83, Folder 15)
    - Man instructing a small group about materials, February 12, 1958 (Box 83, Folder 16)
    - Unloading equipment from flatcase, interior of warehouse at Allegheny Industrial Electrical, March 31, 1959 (Box 83, Folder 17)
    - Student Architect Awards ceremony, May 28, 1958 (Box 83, Folder 18)
    - Children playing games and group shots at Rust company picnic, North Park, Pittsburgh, PA, July 23, 1958 (Box 83, Folder 19)
    - Junior Achievement Awards ceremony, December 17, 1958 (Box 83, Folder 20)
    - Airplane and hanger at Allegheny Airport, December 15, 1958 (Box 83, Folder 21)
    - Architectural award ceremony, May 20, 1959 (Box 83, Folder 22)
    - Science Awards ceremony at Kaufmanns, Pittsburgh, PA, May 21, 1959 (Box 83, Folder 23)
    - Company plane and pilot, Allegheny County Airport, June 30, 1960 (Box 83, Folder 24)
    - Anniversary Party, Webster Hall, October 19, 1960 (Box 83, Folder 25)
    - President S.M. Rust, Jr. in office, June 15, 1961 (Box 83, Folder 26)
    - Company jet at Allegheny Airport, July 19, 1968 (Box 83, Folder 27)
    - Scale model of a structure (Box 83, Folder 28)
    - Winning 3D model by Carnegie Tech students, March 25, 1957 (Box 83, Folder 29)
    - Paul Scheetz, engineers, and draftsmen in the Drawing Room of the Heeran Building, 1948 (Box 83, Folder 30)
    - Three Sisters Bridges and Fort Wayne Railroad Bridge in snow, taken from Rust office, March 3, 1960 (Box 83, Folder 31)
    - Boiler on cart, c1920 (Box 83, Item 1)
    - Chimney for Seaboard By-Product Co., Jersey City, NY, c1920 (Box 83, Item 2)
    - Chimneys for Firestone Tire and Rubber Co., Akron, Ohio, c1920 (Box 83, Item 3)
    - Chimney for Midland Coke Ovens, c1920 (Box 83, Item 4)
    - Stack, Lehigh, PA, c1920 (Box 83, Item 5)
    - Eggners Ferry Bridge being raised, Murray, KY, c1943 (Box 83, Item 06-07)
    - Monitor on roof at Evanston (Box 83, Item 08-09)
    - Boiler brickwork for 10 Franklin boilers, Charleston Con. Ry. Light and Power Co., Charleston, SC, 1911 (Box 83, Item 10-11)
    - Cartoons and caricatures of Rust personnel (negatives), c1960 (Oversize 1)
    - Photo Album of projects for Central Iron and Coal Company, Holt Alabama, 1917-1918 (Box 84)
  - New Materials Added, 1915-1968; 5.
    - Alabama Industries Week Displays, 1959-1960 (Box 85, Folder 1)
    - A.M. Woodall Profile, undated (Box 85, Folder 2)
    - Boston Office (exterior and interior), undated (Box 85, Folder 3)
    - Birmingham Clay Products Company, undated (Box 85, Folder 4)
    - Birmingham Office Library, 1957 (Box 85, Folder 5)
    - Birmingham Office Photos, undated (Box 85, Folder 6)
    - Blood Drive, Janurary, 1959 (Box 85, Folder 7)
    - Chimney Department, Pittsburgh Office, 1964 (Box 85, Folder 8)
    - Company Library in Birmingham, undated (Box 85, Folder 9)
    - Computers, Birmingham and Pittsburgh Offices, 1961 (Box 85, Folder 10)
    - Delivery of Beechcraft Super 18 Airplane, July 1959 (Box 85, Folder 11)
    - Ford Motor Co. Pump House Construction, June 1926 (Box 85, Folder 12)
    - Group Photos, persons named, undated (Box 85, Folder 13)
    - Group Photos, persons unnamed, undated (Box 85, Folder 14)
    - James L. Shaunessy Retirement Dinner, 1961 (Box 85, Folder 15)
    - Jobs, 1915-1916 (Box 85, Folder 16)
    - Junior Achievement Program (Birmingham), 1958-1959 (Box 85, Folder 17)
    - Lloyd Belcher Receiving Check, undated (Box 85, Folder 18)
    - L.S. Barker Receiving Check, 1960 (Box 85, Folder 19)
    - Peddie Ditch Bridge Job, undated (Box 85, Folder 20)
    - Pesonnel Assigned to Expansion of Paper Mill, 1963 (Box 85, Folder 21)
    - Photo Caption without image, 1959 (Box 85, Folder 22)
    - Pomeroy Chemical Co. Plant Construction, October 1918 (Box 85, Folder 23)
    - Portraits (8x10), 1959 (Box 85, Folder 24)
    - Portraits (5x3.5), undated (Box 85, Folder 25)
    - R.D. Spellman Dinner, February 1960 (Box 85, Folder 26)
    - Receptionists Operating Telephone Switchboards, undated (Box 85, Folder 27)
    - Republic Bank Note Company Office Construction, May 1927 (Box 85, Folder 28)
    - Rust Triangle Photos, 1961-1963 (Box 85, Folder 29)
    - Scale Model of Southwest Forest Industries Co. Paper Mill, undated (Box 85, Folder 30)
    - Third Annual Meeting of Sales Department, November 15-16, 1968 (Box 85, Folder 31)
    - Tommie Burleson Receiveing 10-Year Pen, June 1960 (Box 85, Folder 32)
- New Materials Added, 1915-1989; X.
  Scope and Contents
  Additions to the Rust Engineering Company Records contains a variety of records that primarily pertains to Rust's office in Birmingham, Alabama, including correspondence, promotional materials, and employee handbooks. Also includes some materials from various divisions of the company and other locations.
  - Air and Water Pollution Prevention and Control, Informational Brochure, c1970s-1980s (Box 86, Folder 1)
  - Birmingham Office Informational Handbook, 1961 (Box 86, Folder 2)
  - Cement Production Plan Construction, Promotional Brochure, c1970 (Box 86, Folder 3)
  - Chemical Plant Construction, Promotional Material, c1953 (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - Chimney Division, Promotional Material, c1958-1980s (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - Company Morale Report, c1950s-1960s (Box 86, Folder 6)
  - Coppee-Rust, Materials related to merger, 1973 (Box 86, Folder 7)
  - Doyle and Russell, Introductory Handbook to the Company, c1980s (Box 86, Folder 8)
  - Employee Handbook, 1963 (Box 86, Folder 9)
  - Financial Statements, 1965 (Box 86, Folder 10)
  - Founder's Day and Service Award Dinner Program, 1950 (Box 86, Folder 11)
  - Industrial Health Council Informational Pamphlet, 1959 (Box 86, Folder 12)
  - Opening of Birmingham Office, 1966-1967 (Box 86, Folder 13)
  - Organizational Charts, 1970 (Box 86, Folder 14)
  - Paper Mill Construction, Promotional Materials, c1950s-1970s (Box 86, Folder 15)
  - Paper Mill Construction, Procedure Plan, 1938 (Box 86, Folder 16)
  - Pittsburgh Office, mailers announcing move, 1956 (Box 86, Folder 17)
  - Promotional Brochures (various), c1960s-1980s (Box 86, Folder 18)
  - Qualifications and Services Booklet for Doyle and Russell, c1950 (Box 86, Folder 19)
  - Rust Construction (Newsletter), 1969-1971 (Box 87, Folder 1)
  - Rust Furnace Company, Financial Reports, 1965-1966 (Box 87, Folder 2)
  - Rust Furnace Company, Promotional Material, c1970s-1980s (Box 87, Folder 3)
  - Rust International, Promotional Material, c1970s-1980s (Box 87, Folder 4)
  - Saks, Claude M.--Thesis, "An American Eng...." (Duquesne University), 1967 (Box 87, Folder 5)
  - S.M. Rust Jr., Correspondence regarding Doyle and Russell, 1962-1969 (Box 87, Folder 6)
  - Steam Power Division, Promotional Material, c1955 (Box 87, Folder 7)
  - Steel Division, Promotional Material and Handbooks, c1950s-1960s (Box 87, Folder 8)
  - The Parkersburg Sentinel, July 17, 1936 (Box 87, Folder 9)
  - Triangle (Newsletter), 1967-1973 (Box 87, Folder 10)
  - Vibroflotation Division, Promotional Material, c1970s-1980s (Box 87, Folder 11)